<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A serious addresse to Samuel Oates, for a resolve in some few quære's touching his new-baptisme &amp; ministry. Also a short and faithfull word of Christian advice to those of his church in Lincolnshire, concerning their way, and that spirit by which they are led. Together with a brief and plain evidence of the ground for baptizing a believers infant-seed. / By John Drew, a servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Drew, John, fl. 1649-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81742</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864956</idno>
  <idno type="VID">117189</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240919989</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E549_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205636</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864956</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864956e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81742)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117189)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 85:E549[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A serious addresse to Samuel Oates, for a resolve in some few quære's touching his new-baptisme &amp; ministry. Also a short and faithfull word of Christian advice to those of his church in Lincolnshire, concerning their way, and that spirit by which they are led. Together with a brief and plain evidence of the ground for baptizing a believers infant-seed. / By John Drew, a servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Drew, John, fl. 1649-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bartlett, at the guilt Cup at Austins gate or Pauls stump,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 5.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117189:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Serious Addresse</hi> TO Samuel Oates, For a <hi>Resolve</hi> in some few QUAERE'S Touching his <hi>New-Baptisme</hi> &amp; <hi>Ministry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO A short and faithfull word of Christian Advice to those of his Church in <hi>Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> concerning their way, and that spirit by which they are led.</p>
            <p>Together with a brief and plain Evidence of the Ground for Baptizing a <hi>Believers Jnfant-seed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Drew,</hi> a servant of Jesus Christ.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 16.17, 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Now I beseech you Brethren, marke them which cause Divisions and offences, contrary to the Doctrine which yee have learned, and avoid them.</p>
               <p>For they that are such, serve not our Lord Iesus Christ, but their own belly, and by good words and faire speeches deceive the hearts of the simple.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <bibl>
                     <hi>Camerar. è veteri Graec.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Bartlet,</hi> at the guilt Cup at <hi>Austins</hi> gate or <hi>Pauls</hi> stump. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:117189:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117189:2"/>
            <head>To Mr. <hi>Oates;</hi> the reason of publishing these Papers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen our Saviour questioned the <hi>Chiefe Priests,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 11.30.</note>
               <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> about the <hi>Baptisme of Iohn, Mark</hi> 11.30. [which I conceive there to be his Doctrine and Authority for baptizing] <hi>whence it was, from Heaven, or of men? they answered him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">vers. 31.</note>
               <hi>we cannot tell.</hi> And truly, that which was the issue of their reasoning among themselves about that businesse, seemes somewhat, if not very much (in the sense of many) like the result of those publike debates lately had with you in these parts, by some differing from you about your <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Baptism,</hi> and <hi>Authority.</hi> Such as have opposed your <hi>Way</hi> have either been forc't [by reason of the disorder &amp;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> confusion in those meetings, and that wild liberty of discourse you have taken to your self] to give out this answer touching your <hi>Way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> eurip</note>
               <hi>They could not tell whence it was;</hi> or at leastwise, have beene interpreted to have done so, by the greatest number of hearers; the things in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion being never brought to any satisfying head or issue.</p>
            <p>Now that it may not be adjudged by every man, that we know not from whence your <hi>Baptisme</hi> and <hi>Ministry</hi> is, I have adventured in some few <hi>Quaeres</hi> to give out my present thoughts and judgement concerning their paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and Originall, shewing them to be lesse from above then our Baptisme, and the Ministry of the Church of <hi>England</hi> which you make <hi>null</hi> and <hi>Babylonish.</hi> How it will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117189:3"/>be taken by you I know not; but I have observed it is your ordinary course in disputing (contrary to the Lawes of a dispute) to appeal at every hands turne to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple round about, as if you intended to cajole them all to a belief of what you speak, to be truth, whether they think so or not. Therefore I have assumed (though not for that end of yours, yet) the like liberty of appeal to the people, hoping you will be content with the same measure you give. Surely sir, me thinks it should be of great advantage to the truth (if those things you stand by be the truths of God) to put your pen to paper, and assert them publikely amongst us; this will much cleare your way to such as doubt the warrant of it, and cannot come to be of your ordinary hearers: And by this meanes you will gaine many thanks from others, who for the present, are fully perswaded against it; for then they may come to know where to have you, and what to hold you to, (for hitherto something you have held one day, and denied it the next) and assure your selfe, Sir, if you will do thus, you shall be under-taken, if by no strong hands, yet ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then fail, by his weak hand willingly put out for the service of the Gospel, who is a friend to your person, but an enemy to your Errors.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Drew.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117189:3"/>
            <head>A serious Addresse to <hi>Samuel Oates</hi> for resolution in some few important <hi>Quaeres</hi> concerning his <hi>New Baptisme</hi> and MINISTRY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving been present at some of those late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences (that I may not call them Disputes) which have been had publikely betwixt your self and some others about your Doctrine and Practise, I have found no satisfaction at all from them concerning either, though they were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted on purpose to satisfie any man that was contrary minded, as you have declared, and not for your conviction, though upon supposall you were in an Error; (which certainly, you that crie out so vehemently against <hi>Infallibility in Synods, Classes, &amp;c.</hi> must give men leave to suppose till they know why one man may not erre as well as an hundred.) You professe Disputes shall not move you, having perfect rest in your spirit, and full satisfaction already in every point that you hold, and in all things which you practise. And truly Sir, had other men who love the truth and wayes of God as well as your self, the like satisfaction, they would not grutch your successe at all, but rejoyce if the <hi>gleanings</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptisme</hi> were greater then the <hi>vintage of any other way</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession whatsoever; till then, you must not be angry if they reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the way you go in, amongst the first-born of the abhorrings of their souls;
<note place="margin">Jer. 6.16.</note> they cannot but look at it as none of the <hi>good old way,</hi> but as a path utterly untrodden by the feet of Gods people, till of late some have unhappily turned aside to it; neither can they but look at those Errors which lead you along in it, as Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the first magnitude. Suffer me therefore, Sir, who am in the number of these unsatisfied ones, to ease my thoughts of your way a little by giving them vent into some few <hi>Quaeres,</hi> both as a short Essay towards the tryall of your grounds, and as a testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117189:4"/>to the truths and wayes of God as well as against the unheedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of your wayes, by reason of which <hi>the way of truth is evill spoken of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Those things which at present I would gladly have resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in, are these,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quare. </seg>1</label> Whether, to a safe and right <hi>Administration</hi> of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptisme, there be not as necessarily required <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in the <hi>Administrator,</hi> as Faith. Confession of sins and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance (without which conditions, Baptisme you say, is a nullitie) in the subjects to whom this Ordinance is to be administred? If this be denied, I do not see but every man (at least) every belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is as lawfull an administrator as <hi>Samuel Oates;</hi> neither do I see why <hi>Baptisme</hi> by a Midwife (supposing the subjects right to it) can be disapproved, as thwarting the mind of Jesus Christ at all; Nay lastly,
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19</note> I see no reason why <hi>Go yee,</hi> as a restrictive term should be inserted in the Apostles Commission from Christ, or how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there should be any Commission at all, though God be the God of Order. But if this be granted, as what sober man without some face of reason will stick at it? Then in the next place I must claim a little help from you for my resolution.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere. </seg>2</label> How your self or any <hi>Rebaptizer</hi> comes by this Authority?
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.18</note> if you have it immediately from <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> who is his Fathers <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotentiary,</hi> you must either shew us a new Commission (which I suppose you scarce pretend to have) or else make it appeare that by an immediate call from <hi>Jesus</hi> our <hi>King,</hi> your name is put into that old <hi>Commission, Matth.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Go yee therefore and teach all Nations baptizing them, &amp;c.</hi> which Call as well as the former is extraordinary, having no Mediety at all of man in it; if this be the Resolve I must be faine to take up withall; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> great is my Dis-satisfaction not onely in regard it opens a doore to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of pretenders as well as <hi>S. O.</hi> yea to any man in the world who lists to plead the like Call; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but, Secondly, because it utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly layes aside and Nuls that ordinary way of authorising <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strators</hi> which <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> has left to his <hi>Church,</hi> viz. that medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate setting apart of persons approved by the hands of others in his name, and by his Authority, to whom this power belongs, I question not now, sure I am 'tis an Ordinance of <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:117189:4"/>1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21, 22. and he that by pretending an unusuall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Call or Power from <hi>Christ</hi> waves this <hi>Institution</hi> (since the rule of Scripture was perfected) shall finde our great Ruler as jealous for it as for any other Ordinance he has left us, yea as dreadfull as that Scripture renders him, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.18, 19. Nay, Lastly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in regard I cannot see the <hi>Lord</hi> giving any <hi>testimony</hi> that you are thus of him, I must take leave to aske with the
<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 2.18</note> Jewes, <hi>What Signe shewest thou unto us, seeing thou doest these things?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 5.36. Matth. 11.4, 5, 6.</note> Our Saviour in the point of his mission referres us to the Fathers wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse by his <hi>works,</hi> and would not attest his ministry himself, no not to <hi>John</hi> the Baptist; but <hi>shew John,</hi> saith he, <hi>those things which yee do heare and see, &amp;c.</hi> God never sets up any man as a wonder to the world, without a wonderfull concurrence of his power and presence with him. Now Sir,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.30.</note> where is your gift of <hi>tongues,</hi> your <hi>miracles?</hi> or <hi>interpretation of tongues?</hi> These I know you pretend not to, nor (for ought I hear) to any gifts but what are usually found in men ordinarily called; but an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary call never wanted the evidence of extraordinary Abilities or Qualifications in one kind or other; therefore I believe your Claime is not thus broad, unlesse by consequence and interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it prove so; for he who affirms that every believer has the like Call from God to Preach and Baptize that the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> had, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. affirmeth himself, if he be a Believer, to be immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately and extraordinarily called, (this I dare trust without any proof for its truth, besides that rehearsall of the Apostles Call, <hi>Acts</hi> 26, 16, 17, 18.) But this Proposition was Mr.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Febr.</hi> 8.</note>
               <hi>Oates</hi> his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, and I leave others then to judge of what parentage the consequence is, and whether <hi>S. O</hi> must not neede own the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion if these premises stand true? but though you disclaim and disavow your pretence to any such Call in plaine termes, yet I perswade my selfe Sir, you are not ignorant that our Generation brings forth many who blush not to stand by it, and let that be my Apology for heightning the saucinesse of any such pretence; &amp; let me tel you, were there any men really so called, their works like lightning would open to us the cloud from whence they dropt; they need not be pointed at by this man, that man,
<note place="margin">Mark 5.7. Acts 19.15. Act. 16.17.</note> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man indeed, the very Devils would cry out of them and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them.</p>
            <p>But now Sir, if you have your <hi>Authority</hi> from <hi>Christ mediately,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117189:5"/>viz.</hi> from the <hi>Church</hi> (for so I understand you sometimes profess your self called) then my next <hi>Quaere</hi> will be this;</p>
            <p n="3">3. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere </seg>3</label> Whether came your Call, from a Church in order, built up according to that which you account the true Gospel platforme, or from a company of Believers out of that Gospel form, or Order, <hi>viz.</hi> ungathered? I suppose it cannot come from the latter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause you deny the Ministry of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be a true Ministry, chiefly from this very ground; because not called by a Church, that is, a Society of persons, men and women re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized and gathered into Order, according to your <hi>Way;</hi> which ground, though to me, it be an abominable one, as denying in effect that God ever had a Church true in respect of form [which I conceive to be the <hi>Esse constitutivum</hi> of a <hi>Church</hi>] till Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme with her Rule and Compasse squared it exactly yet I say, this ground will serve me to build an Argument, <hi>Ad hominem,</hi> even against your self, upon; If Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was called by lively stones out of any spirituall building which had not <hi>Rebaptization</hi> written upon the door, his Call was <hi>Antichristian,</hi> from his own principles; or if from any single man or society of men, officed or unofficed, out of this Order, it is the same; take heed Sir, there may be gray haires here and there upon you, though you know it not; therefore I suppose that to avoid your being dasht out of office against the Rock of your own principles, you must needs be called from a rebaptized Congregation, and if so, then</p>
            <p n="4">4. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere </seg>4</label> Whether was this Church of your own gathering, or of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans? if of your own gathering, then you gathered them without a Call; for according to your self they could not elect or call you till they were baptized, and in that way of Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship or Order, which you are bold to call <hi>Gospel Order,</hi> or <hi>Forme.</hi> And then, if you were not sent immediately from Christ, you ran before you were sent or duly called by a <hi>Church,</hi> and so the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Baptisme of that Congregation was Null, because you were not an Authorized Administrator according to our first <hi>Quaere.</hi> Surely therefore that Church from which you received your Call and Ministerial power was of another mans Gathering and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, and you your self first a Member gathered and baptized by him. If so, then</p>
            <p n="5">5. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere </seg>5</label> Who called that man to gather and baptize those living stones built up by him into that Church whereof you were a Mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber?
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117189:5"/>if your self and those other baptized ones with you, then his Calling was <hi>Null,</hi> because you were not formed into that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as to make you capable of calling a Minister, being unbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; And your Baptism received by his Administration was <hi>null,</hi> because to you he could not be an Authorized Administrator.</p>
            <p>Thus in going a few steps backward, you must necessarily hang all the weight of your new Baptisme and Calling, either</p>
            <p n="1">1. Upon one that was a <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>baptizer,</hi> that is, who <hi>baptized himselfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or 2. Upon one who rested content with his owne infant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptisme. If you stand to the latter of these stakes, then I would gladly know</p>
            <p n="6">6. How you can prove it necessary, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere. </seg>6</label> that every man must be rebaptized before he can be a member of a visible Church, if one may be a Minister of such a Church, who contents himselfe with his Infant-baptisme only? if you stand to the former, then I Quaere</p>
            <p n="7">7. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere. </seg>7</label> What Ground had that Person to warrant and make good his <hi>Selfe-baptization?</hi> I commend you for sticking close to the Rule for positive worship as you seem to do, when for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son you impugne and nullifie Infant-baptisme, because there's no Command in Scripture, as you say, either <hi>t<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tidem verbis,</hi> or by good Consequence to warrant it. I hope such as cry out most against will-worship, dare not invent an institution; surely those that tell others they do nothing, if they bring not a Command for what they do in <hi>way</hi> of Ordinance, will hold out such grounds for their practice, as he that runs may read them. But I do seriously professe that I have stayed my selfe from running, and have leisurely weighed every Precept, and narrowly look't into the practice of <hi>Baptisme</hi> in the Gospell, yet I could never see but alwayes the <hi>Administrator</hi> and the <hi>Subject</hi> to which <hi>Baptisme</hi> was administred, were two different Persons; I cannot see either <hi>vola</hi> or <hi>vestigium,</hi> print or footstep of Se-baptization in the Scripture, though <hi>I</hi> would set my selfe in the greatest po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture of indulgence, toward the maintaining of that practice that possibly <hi>I</hi> could.
<note place="margin">John 3.23. John 4.2.</note>
               <hi>I</hi> have read of <hi>John</hi> baptizing some of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Jesus, with <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> and the Eunuch, baptizing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but of a Se-baptizer, <hi>nè</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>quidem,</hi> not one title. <hi>I</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade my selfe that the Apostles, and so all their Successors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117189:6"/>to the Letter of their Commission, said thus to every one they Baptized, <hi>I baptize thee in the name of the Father, &amp;c.</hi> but I never heard of one that said so to himself. Surely <hi>I</hi> &amp; <hi>Thee</hi> are two different Subjects, and unlesse a man wrong the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar of the Text, he cannot baptize himselfe. Of the two, there were more colour, (could it consist with the Anabaptists Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,) for one to begin Re-baptizing, that never renounc't his old baptisme, then a <hi>Se-baptizer;</hi> for he that disclaims his Infant-baptisme, is an unbaptized Person ever, if not rebaptized, and finding none to baptize him, his <hi>Sebaptisme</hi> is <hi>ipso facto</hi> null, and so hee is an unbaptized Person still, who having torne off the Seale of his Covenant with God, cannot dispense the Seale to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; an unbaptized Person is out of the Church, say you: and then say I he can let none in;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28.</note> God, saith the Apostle, sets his Administrators, <hi>viz.</hi> Apostles, Prophets, Evangelists, Pastors, &amp;c. in the Church; they are Church-members, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4. but one that renounceth not his Infant-Seale, might with some shew alledge for his practice of Re-baptizing, that of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptist, who was never baptized that we read of, but retained his Infant-zeale of Circumcision.</p>
            <p>Yet neither will this helpe the Rebaptizer, unlesse he can prove himself sent to begin a new institution, as <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptist was,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.9.</note> yea, and as extraordinary a person, even <hi>more then a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But suppose Sir, you had a third nayle, and that a surer one whereon you might hang the weight of your new Baptisme and Calling, <hi>viz.</hi> An Administrator from some Church of Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists beyond the seas, in <hi>Holland,</hi> or some other place, (I do but guesse Sir, because I know not to what shelter you may betake your selfe,) so that may be <hi>S. O.</hi> was baptized by Mr. <hi>Lambe,</hi> and Mr. <hi>L.</hi> by some rebaptized Minister of a forreigne Church; upon this account the matter would be little the better. For then I Quaere</p>
            <p n="8">8. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere </seg>8</label> How came he to be your Minister? by what Authority did he baptize that first Person in <hi>England?</hi> who baptized Mr. <hi>Lamb?</hi> To baptize is an action of office and power; but how could this man be an Officer, or a lawfull Administrator to him or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, before there were any baptized Persons capable of electing him to that Authority or Ministry? Either retract this Principle
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117189:6"/>Sir, that believers out of Order and not rebaptized, or [as you call it] unbaptized, cannot call a Minister, or your Calling and Baptisme is easily driven to a nullity. But I beleeve you had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hazzard that, then raze so prime a pillar of your building. For that Principle being once retracted, the Ministry of <hi>England</hi> is acknowledged a true Ministry rightly called: and with that same breath you call your self a Schismatick and a Railer against what you knew not, a wandring Star,
<note place="margin">Jude 13.</note> a Subverter of unstable Souls, yea one that hath fed upon ashes,
<note place="margin">Esa. 44.1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and now saith was there not a lie in my right hand?</p>
            <p>But supposing [though I grant it not] that you had a direct and lawfull Call from a Church in <hi>Norfolke</hi> to a pastorall charge there, for thus I remember I have heard you tell people, yet</p>
            <p n="9">9. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere </seg>9</label> How should we be satisfied in these parts where you are of your calling hither, and of the warrant you have for those Administrations which you exercise your self about, amongst us, those officiall duties of preaching and baptizing, if you stand to your often-mentioned Principle, <hi>That a Church ungathered can give no call?</hi> how many Persons in <hi>Lincolne-shire</hi> did you finde re-baptized, to give you entertainment as their Pastor, if you baptized those People which make up your Church, before they were in a capacity of calling you? their Baptisme (as is evinced already) must be null, you being to them at least, no authoriz'd Administrator, if you say you were a Minister before, thats no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to them, you were an <hi>Individuum vugum</hi> for all that. Could they be in an order or <hi>way</hi> for electing you for their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, being unbaptized Persons; besides I know 'tis against your Rule to say you were a Minister of Jesus Christ, when you came to baptize them; for your Principles cannot allow of an <hi>indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Minister;</hi> if you have no flock, certainly no <hi>Anabaptist</hi> will acknowledge you a Pastor: and I have known you contest a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Ordination before Election as Anti-christian. Certainly Christians in these parts, thoughly they honour a sent Ministry, will desire to see what warrant a Congregation in <hi>Norwich</hi> hath, to send a Minister amongst them, before they can submit to him. They are not such <hi>Presbyterians</hi> as can acknowledge any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in <hi>England</hi> for their Classis, to approve an Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strator to lead them they know not whether, in a new way of Ordinance; they hate blind obedience, but love clear light, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117189:7"/>it be new or old; and I feare Sir, if the matter were well scan'd, they have had little of this light from you; you have rais'd a dust amongst us; in stead of unfilming our eyes, helpt us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to confusion, in crying out against us as Babylonish; thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our darknesse, rather then brought us into <hi>Goshen;</hi> you have made many disputers, but I feare, very few believers. And if you rob real Churches, to gather to your self a formal one; pick and pilfer away none but <hi>hewen stones</hi> to lay in your building; I'le say, he knowes little, and loves the truth lesse, that thinks he may adventure, or will go about to acquit you of sacriledge.</p>
            <p>But I am somewhat too far from your <hi>Call</hi> now, which is that thing I would fain meet with. If you came not hither as a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> in the common usage of the word; yet (as I think you have hinted) it is lawfull to minister as a gifted brother, and so you might do in way of probation to their electing you. This may be granted; and were it possible [saving your Principles] for them to elect before their Baptisme, it might advantage you: but since that cannot be, you are as far from being their Minister still, as when you were at <hi>Norwich;</hi> for then, I think, you were their Brother. But,</p>
            <p n="10">10. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere. </seg>10</label> How come you to step so suddenly from a brotherly to an official Ministry? such I understand Baptisme to be: for if it be a Brotherly ministry, we are all bound to baptize one another as oft as we meet together for edification: but surely 'tis the act of an empowerd Administrator; and how you should be so to them, while unbaptiz'd, is the thing that I would very gladly learn of you.</p>
            <p>Could you tie such a knot as this upon the Ministry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> [pardon that expression (sir) I call that one Church which indeed is many, as the Apostle doth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 2.] I believe you would dare the whole world to untie it: If the stars in that firmament were no better fixt then you appeare to be, I am perswaded your train had thrown down not onely the third part of them,
<note place="margin">Rev. 12, 4. Rev. 2, 1. Joh. 10 29.</note> but three parts, if not all four, long before this day. But surely Jesus Christ has them in his right hand; and though your Doctrine of falling from Grace makes it an easie matter to pluck his sheep out of his hand, yet you'll find it hard getting his shepherds from thence: though you look at them as your greatest enemies, they are sure Christ will own them for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117189:7"/>his
<note n="*" place="margin">Jo. 15.14.</note> friends. And now I have done with your Ministry, suffer me one <hi>Quaere</hi> touching that Ministry, the subjects whereof are commonly called Priests by your self and your contumelious fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; even the Ministry of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I desire you seriously to think of satisfying me in this.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether any man may safely perswade himself, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere. </seg>11</label> that Jesus Christ will so far owne an Antichristian Ministry, as to honour it with converting millions of souls to himself? Can that power which in its nature is directly contrary to him, and of implacable enmity against him, [for such is the very essence of whatever is Antichristian] can that, I say, possibly do Jesus Christ such service as this? If any souls have been fed up to life, and nourisht by the Ministry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jo. 21.17.</note> 'tis an argument of its love toward, and not enmity against Jesus Christ. The Lord would not honour <hi>David</hi> with the building him an house,
<note place="margin">1 Chron. 28, 3. Ps. 116, 15. Rev. 17.6.</note> because he had been a man of war and shed blood; yet <hi>Davids</hi> wars were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: but Antichrist making war against the Lamb, hath been drunken with the blood of the Saints, (whose death is precious in Gods eyes) and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jesus; and will the Lord (think you) honour Antichrist so far as to suffer any Ministry or Order of his setting up, to build him an house? surely no. 'Tis an invincible argument that they are arrowes of Christs sending, even out of his bow,
<note place="margin">Esa. 60.8. 1 Cor. 9.2. 2 Cor. 10.18.</note> when they hit the mark he aims at so right. They are factours for Jesus Christ, surely, that bring soules to him, <hi>as the doves to the windowes.</hi> Christ in this <hi>sets to his seal</hi> that the Ministry is his: 'tis not to be thought, sir, he would <hi>reveale his arme so mightily,</hi> in an Order set up meerly to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw his kingdome, as whatsoever Antichrist sets up is. And I am verily perswaded, Soules have been built up as surely to salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by their hands, (call them <hi>Babylonish,</hi> if you please) as ever they are like to be by yours; though you would have us think, believers were never built up as spiritual houses, in <hi>England,</hi> till they were blest with a second Baptisme. If they were built up and edified to heaven, I hope you'l not tell them, you can build them better. I have read this Phrase in an
<note n="*" place="margin">Tertul. <hi>aedisicant in ruinam.</hi> De praescr. haeret. 1 Cor. 3.10</note> old Writer, by him applied to some lately-revived Hereticks; <hi>They are built up,</hi> saith he <hi>or edified to destruction.</hi> I pray God your building prove not such at length, even a taking poor soules off from that <hi>sure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> laid for them ministerially by such builders and workmen
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117189:8"/>
               <hi>as need not be ashamed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> and a setting them up at last so high and tottering above Ordinances and above duties, that they fall: If so, their fall will be very great; I should weep over, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce at their ruine; and the Lord grant I never see it. This I know, Errour is unstedfast, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. and when we are <hi>wise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what is convenient,</hi> we know not where to rest. Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptisme,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saltmarsh, Den,</hi> (as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) and others.</note> ere long, may be rejected by your self, and left off or laid aside as a carnal rite, as it is already by very many formerly of your way: and what will be your Churches form then, I know not. Men give themselves up to Sceptisme and uncertainty in Judgment, by stepping one foot beyond the line of Truth; one Error must have at least two more for its supporters; and when one Truth is undermined, the whole kingdome of Truth shakes. Hence it is that many wild Opinionists,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Errori assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itas, quippe dubitatio species in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scitiae.</hi> Scal. exer. 148.</note> that make Religion like a Feather, are so unresolved what to fixe upon, that like a man treading upon thorns, they step here and there, and stand still no where: They see that striking at one Truth, wounds so many, and Truth having yet a kind of secret awe over their hearts, they do but make ventures, and hit upon nothing. Were it not better sir, to feed and nourish men up with satisfying truths, then always to keepe up their appetites after Novelty? to endeavour the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment of their hearts with grace, as the Ministry of <hi>England</hi> hath done,
<note place="margin">Heb 13.9.</note> then to loosen them from a liking of sound doctrine by vaine janglings, as some preaching out of envy have done? I am perswaded confidently, that as Christ hath owned, so he will ever owne that Ministry which begets found hearts, above that which brings forth disputing heads.</p>
            <p>He knowes but very little in this businesse, who knowes not that as much has been said against the Ministry of the Church of <hi>England</hi> formerly by men [hatcht under that very Ministry to Faith in Jesus and a Gospel profession by their own acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment] ringleaders to a Separation as a state of higher purity (which might be granted without any milling of that Ministry) nay more has been spoken by those persons to this point then <hi>S. O.</hi> is able to say;
<note place="margin">Robinson Canne, &amp;c.</note> all which notwithstanding in the judgement of sober and advised Christians never amounted to such a summe as would <hi>Antichristianize</hi> that Ministry. They have been as heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse in drawing up their Charge as your selfe, but as weak in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging it against the Ministry as those Jewes <hi>Acts</hi> 25.7. <hi>who laid
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117189:8"/>many and grievous complaints against</hi> Paul <hi>which they could not prove;</hi> you have hung as heavie weights as they upon smaller threats, and if all they gain'd being cast up, was but a disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their Fathers shame, some blemishes and corruptions both in their calling and exercise of their Functions (which the godly <hi>Nonconformists</hi> both saw, and declaim'd against as well as they, but could not then get remedy] what further advantage your accusations will have against them, I am not able to discern; tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I know no men (unlesse they be <hi>Seekers,</hi>) who have any ballast of Christian warinesse or preadvision at all wherewith to weigh their Judgements, that dare say, there never was a true Ministry in the Church since the Apostles Age till now: but this must needs follow, if those grounds you build upon be able to bear up your charge; for it is an easie matter to find out corruptions, [greater then any you can now shew,] cleaving to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry in all ages since the Apostles; and if that be sufficient to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it Anti christian, then Christ hath had no true Ministry for 1500 years at least; and it is as strongly conclusive too against Magisteriall power, even that male-administration should ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Order of Magistracy to be no Ordinance of God. But they must be stronger blasts then these Sir, that blow the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry of <hi>England</hi> to a nullity; you must prove that Ministeriall power cannot be in the hands of a wicked person, and then you do something; for if it may be in the hands of such a Person, why may it not be derived from his hands? if you say it cannot be in his hands, then you must prove <hi>Indas, Demas</hi> and <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> to be no Ministers, and this will go a great way towards the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what we desire to see. Let me tell you Sir, if to all the strength of your Arguments, you should call in that more base ignoble aide of swords and pistols, hornes and hoofs, you could not nullifie the Minstry of <hi>England;</hi> we yield you stand upon the higher ground in this respect to the nulling of it, and [if such a way might stand with your principles] to the laying the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry as flat as the wals of <hi>sericho;</hi> but though I pretend not to prophecy, yet I beleeve that <hi>S. O.</hi> will scarce have his joyes made so full while he lives, as this would make them: Ministers may be, and are very like to be brought to a lesse well-being, [which is a kind of a
<note n="*" place="margin">Media scilicet natura in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter esse &amp; non esse minus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne esse. <hi>Scal.</hi>
               </note> middle state betwixt an <hi>esse</hi> and a <hi>non esse</hi>] but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to a <hi>non</hi>-being; though the taking away or impairing their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117189:9"/>livelihood and outward subsistence may bring them very low, yet pray remember Sir, this is a weak Argument to prove their Calling a nullity; you may easily prove them poore by this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, but scarcely Anti-christian. One thing more is yet hehinde that I must intreat satisfaction in.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere. </seg>12</label> Whether default of that outward forme and order of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship amongst the Members of Christ, [which may be nearest to the rule,] can be of that importance with any heart gracious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wise, though but gently charitable, as to unchurch the People of God, for Ages and Generations together, as not to allow them the name of a spirituall building or house, but only of so many stones amongst rubbish,
<note place="margin">Jude 16.25.</note> an indigested heape, or a meere confusion, because not exactly formed up to that Platforme? If the want of this externall forme, [for the inward and essentiall forme is faith,] be not of such weight as to unchurch them, then give me leave to tell you that your inconsideration and rashnesse in thus humbling all beleevers not of your way, and your lavish censures of all formes but your owne, will be required at your hands, by that God who judgeth rightly, and is jealous of his Peoples honour.</p>
            <p>But if it be of such importance, then I think no man can as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure himselfe, that since the Primitive Age God ever had a Church; for though we have testimony sufficient even from their sufferings, for the faith of a thousand times ten thousand, yet we have no witnesse at all, that any company of believers in any Generation since that time, came up so close to the Rule in point of forme and Order, but they might have come up closer. And I am afraid that if this whole kingdome would now come up to your darling, forme or way, we should presently have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other held out as neerer the Rule then it. O Sir, me thinks this should make you mingle your drinke with weeping, even to hear the faith and zeale of Gods old Servants, by any men, thus cast to the Moles and Bats, thus tumbled into the dark hole of invisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, [for Christians without that Gospel order which may serve the turn, are not visible,] rather then [as one glorying in the abundance of his own light, and making sport with other mens blindnesse] thus to lay more weight upon their weaknes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and if they were any way vile, to make them yet more vile by unchurching them your selfe, which censure to a sober know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117189:9"/>Christian is almost of as killing a found as <hi>Anathema Mara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natha.</hi> Nay, Sir,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.22.</note> not only the Churches of God before us but all those now amongst us, if not of your way, are served with the same hand. 'Tis not enough for you to dash all the Infants in <hi>England,</hi> by one heedlesse stroke, out of Covenant with God; even those little Lambs which have not attained to the Actings of Faith and Repentance, out of the hedge of Christs sheepfold into the verge of Satans kingdom, with Jews, Turks, Pagans, &amp;c. But you make strange havock, spoile and vastation amongst those of riper years, un-churching many, who otherwise are your best friends, as the <hi>Brownists,</hi> the <hi>rigid Separatists,</hi> yea and all those Churches of the Congregational way [commonly called <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent</hi>] which the very Presbyterians honour and look at as true Churches, yea very neer to the Rule in point of forme: And all this, because they submit not to a second Baptisme, and will not be so prodigal of their own comforts, and of their Childrens pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, as you would have them. If you say you do not thus, then how can you make Rebaptizing necessary to the forme of a true Church? Certainly, sir, your charity is lesse then your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or else your knowledge is very small. Nay, yet further, this mad rashnesse stayes not here, [if we may believe a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baily</hi> Disswas. 2 <hi>part.</hi>
               </note> Witnesse in this Case, who knows more of the wayes of your Churches, I am perswaded, then you your self do] but to them of your way, the small remnant of Christians in Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptistick societies, which alone they honour with the title of true Churches, seem even too many to be saved: therefore new Separations are run into, and those so severe that there lives not one Anabaptist upon earth, who by multitudes even of Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, is not condemned, with all who adhere to his sub-division, as a man in a false way, not only without, but in opposition to the true Church.</p>
            <p>You may give me leave to make mention sometimes of the Judgment of those of your own way, with reflection upon your self; since in your disputes, you will needs have all the Ministers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> hold the same thing, whether they will or no: I hope you will readily receive that Law you give; and then why may not I say, 'tis your judgment, <hi>That some Societies of Anabaptists are not true Churches?</hi> And then sir, take heed you be not unchurcht your self.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:117189:10"/>
            <p> But 'tis safer inferring any thing from the common Principles of your way, then from the Practise of any man, or society of men. Satisfie me therefore in those things which I have fairly deduced from your own grounds, against that Ministry and those Churches which I am perswaded are true; and it shall not much trouble me to hear those Churches censured, which I have good ground to think are false; as your subdivided Anabaptistick societies may be, for ought I can say or see to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Sir, if I shall receive satisfaction from you in these few <hi>Quaere's,</hi> either as publikely as I desire it, or otherwise as you think best; I must promise you to fall down before the Truth, and that as soon as it appeares to me; yea, I shall readily give up that lot and portion which as yet I retain in the Ministry, and shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your way [though not the only true form of Church-Communion] yet at least the truest of all others. And this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage you will have from your pains, even the gaining one from the error of his wayes. I am none of those that shut mine eyes against light, let it come in at what crevise it will. I am perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, I shall be <hi>led into all Truth;</hi> and if by your hand as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument, I be led out of any <hi>Errour,</hi> I shall <hi>glorifie the God of truth</hi> in you,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.24.</note> and publikely disavow my pertinacie of what I am yet very hesitant in, yea confident that till further conviction I ought not to cast away or part withall. But if that satisfaction come not from you, or elswhere; I must constantly continue, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that enmity in my Judgment against your Principles, an avowed enemy to your wayes; and I am confident I shall ever be willing to <hi>spend and be spent</hi> for the vindication of Gods sacred Truths and Ordinances,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> and to lay out those small talents I have received, towards the establishment of his people in grace, notwithstanding the <hi>cunning craftinesse</hi> of any that shall <hi>lie in wait to deceive.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:117189:10"/>
            <head>A short word of Advice to those of M. <hi>Oates</hi> his Church in <hi>Lincolnshire,</hi> touching their way, and that spirit by which they are led.</head>
            <head>With a brief and plaine Evidence of the ground for Baptizing the Infants of Believers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Christian Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Apostle tels us it is a good thing that the heart be establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with grace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.9. and when I duly consider from what ground he layes that truth home to the Hebrewes, I cannot but wonder it is no greater a startling then indeed it is, to men of unsteady spirits in their entertainment of divers colourd Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, or Doctrines of a different thread, as the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> word there used sometimes signifies. Now the Apostles ground was this, even their ready complyance with any thing that was handed out unto them under the name and Title of Truth, every Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to the mind of God, every one that could but say, lo, here is Christ, or lo, there is Christ,
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.23.</note> that could but tell them this is according to Scripture, or that is according to Scripture, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently won both their eares and their affections, as appears by his endeavour to beat them out of this Grace-weakning temper, by an earnest exhortation to the contrary, <hi>Be not you carried about with diverse and strange Doctrines;</hi> upon this ground he ballasts them with this stable and weighty truth,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chrysost.</note>
               <hi>for it is a good thing that your heart &amp;c.</hi> whence I thinke may be easily gathered, that to be carried about with divers and strange Doctrines, argues an heart unestablished with grace. Far be it from me friends, in the application of this, to charge the meanest of you as void of grace; but give me leave to pray that the God of grace would bring back your hearts to an establishment in the love of those solid Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel-truths and doctrines of grace, with which many of you have been glad to be acquainted formerly, though of late you adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117189:11"/>to reckon them amongst Doctrines,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.12.</note> that are no better then hay and stubble, if not much worse, Anti christian and Divellish. Nothing hath the happinesse of so ready an entrance into Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples heads, as insinuations that they are not taught so well as they might be.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Nazian.</note> Novelty is the rarest Cook in the world, this garnish sets off any dish to Palats of a variable rellish; but that Christians, who of old were upbraided with steady adherence to their principles, as an
<note n="*" place="margin">Obstina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio fidei. Tert. Apol. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Gal.</note> obstinacie of faith, should be now consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of such lightnesse, as like children to be easily tost too and fro with every weak blast of errour, may be the worlds astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and may cause every faithfull Sonne of truth to sigh, even to the breaking of his loynes; For the Gospell-enemies must needs set up their banner, when this is told in <hi>Gath,</hi> and publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the streets of <hi>Askelon.</hi> The Papists could never gaine that advantage against the Gospell by their inquisitions, sword, fire and faggot, which by a few subtile deceivers of late is put into their hands, without any stir at all, yea and that under a varnish and pretence of Gospell-advancement. The Bee hath been an Embleme of a Christian, for their similar properties of Agility, care and usefull Chymistry;
<note place="margin">—saepe lapillos tollunt, his sese per Inania nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bila li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brant. <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </note> I can but wish now that we could learne to imitate those creatures in one thing more, which Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralists observe in them, and thats this, in their flying they use when tis stormy to poize themselves with little gravel stones, as a ship with ballast, that they be not carried away with the winde; but alas, multitudes of Professors in our Generation are not thus wise; for if any winde of doctrine does but fill their sailes, they are ready without any weight or ballast of Christian warinesse to launch forth into the deep, not fearing rocks or shelves, or without fore-thinking indeed whether that winde drives, to what port or harbour, and so make shipwrack of themselves, Grace being not the Pilot,
<note place="margin">Jude 13.</note> but some swelling conceits or vaine ends of their owne, which at length falling into the waves, leave them there to fome out their owne shame.
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.14.</note> Any Doctrine [though delivered by such as use a Text of Scripture,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chrys. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as cheaters do a die] if guilded with the name of Christ be it never so poison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, a pill is swallowed; is it the Lord? saith <hi>Peter,</hi> and he girt his fishers coat unto him, and cast himselfe into the sea, but I know not whether ever Christ gave him thanks for it, or no.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:117189:11"/>
            <p> But I shall forget my self in declaming against this giddy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit amongst us,
<note place="margin">Joh. 21 7. Mat. 17 15</note> this devill that often throws us into the fire and into the water, how he got in amongst us the Lord knows; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall I spend time in enquireing after that. I never read that the Disciples askt how the uncleane spirits and devills came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the possessed ones; but their work was alwayes an endeavour to cast them out.</p>
            <p>Something I have propounded unto your leader <hi>S. O.</hi> as an unsatisfied man about his new Baptisme and ministry, trampling under foot the ministry of the Church of England; And that which I would intreat you his followers, without prejudice to look upon from me as one that is a partaker of the same Hope with your selves, is this; <hi>viz.</hi> A brief examination of the warrantablenesse of that chiefe thing which submits you to his Ministry, even your second Baptisme; this I conceive you are led unto by judging your <hi>Infant-baptisme</hi> a nullity. If therefore the Infants right to that Ordinance be confirmed. I shall easily have the unwarrantablenesse of your late dipping granted me. 'Tis not my designe, Friends, as one that strives for mastery to make any huge flourish with multitude of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (which usually at last fall into one) or to make a noyse with many vaine words;
<note place="margin">Magis of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendit ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium quàm pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>Cicero</hi> Eccles. 12.11. Exod. 27.12.</note> I will contend for this truth but with one weapon [for since I must needs offend you, Ile do it with the least, if it be possible] I shall give you but one reason sharpned and pointed from Scripture, which is given me, as a naile from that Supreme Shepherd Jesus Christ in the behalfe of his little ones, to be fastned in the hearts of all such as prize Gospel Priviledges; one witnesse of this credit will answer for all Believers children in the world; one reall Rod (like that of <hi>Aaron</hi>) will swallw up all the Magicians Rods that lie before it. It is a command from Scripture for <hi>Infant baptisme</hi> that you seek, and complaine that no man is able to shew it you. Now sirs, though I be the weakest Champion for truth, of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands in our <hi>Israel,</hi> yet I dare undertake to clear up this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand unto any unbiast and indifferent man. To bring you a command from Scripture in thus many words and Syllables no man ever went about; and if onely this will suffice you, even to shew such a Text as this. Go yee and Baptize the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of believers, 'tis no marvaile you complaine for want of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117189:12"/>satisfaction. That man who wil undertake to make it good to me under the Gospell, that I ought not to Marry my Sister, or my Daughter, that I ought to keep the first day as the Lords day, or that my wife might partake of the Lord Supper, shall find it a very hard task, if I be resolv'd to take nothing for proofe but a plaine text of Scripture from the Gospel commanding the one and forbidding the other. Friends there are few men in their right witts who professe Christianity, but will readily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that what is fairly drawn from Scripture is as true as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though not formall Scripture; for 'tis impossible that any lye should be raised from that which is truth; thus by good conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence 'tis easily proved that now, the first day of the week is the Christian Sabbath or Lords day; that a woman as well as a man may eate the Supper; &amp;c. and if you see a command fairely riseing from any Scripture, or scriptures, layd together for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptisme, it is as much in effect as if Christ should have said I command you all that believe in me to Baptize your children; if you think not so, then let me desire you that the next time you hear Master <hi>Oates</hi> raise any Doctrine, or Doctrines from Scripture, you would tell him he may not do so; commands by consequence are not binding, if it be not somewhere else in Scripture in so many words, you may not receive it; and when he applies any thing to you from the Word as a truth of God to be imbraced, bid him shew it you in the very words he delivers it to you from Scripture, or else, tell him he does nothing. Friends, do not allow that liberty to one man which you deny to another, this is not faire deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; if that be not truth, or not binding which ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth fairely from the Word, I pray you take heed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving or submitting to any word or syllable in his sermon that is not expresse text of Scripture; but now to proceed. I shall undertake to prove <hi>Infant-baptisme</hi> as fairely to arise by good consequence from Scripture as M. <hi>Oates</hi> shall be to prove any Doctrine that ever he delivered to you which was not in so many words in some other place. I suppose it will not be denied that all along under the old administration of the Covenant of grace from <hi>Abraham</hi> till Christ, all the Infants of of those in Covenant with God were signed with the first
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.11, 12.</note> signe or seale of the Covenant then instituted and commanded by the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117189:12"/>Lord which was <hi>Circumcision;</hi> I meane all the Infants naturally capable of that signe; he that can read the Scripture, will not stick at this, and then my argument runs thus.</p>
            <p>Where there is the same reason of a Precept or command, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>
               </label> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning any practise continued, there may and must be the same practise continued.</p>
            <p>For, when God gives the reason of any command, that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is the ground of the command; and till that reason ceaseth, he is very bold with God that dare exempt himself from the practise. Now to assume; but the reason of the command for sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants of Covenanters with the first Signe or Seale of the Covenant under the Old <hi>Testament</hi> continues still in force for that practise under the New <hi>Testament;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore now that Command is in force to all persons in Covenant as well as it was then.
<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor clear'd</note> If the first Proposition be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, <hi>viz.</hi> where there is the same reason of a Precept conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, there must be the same practise; then every man may set himselfe free from any command of God, <hi>and who can say unto him, what doest thou?</hi> for the Lord commands nothing without a reason; if there be no reason exprest, the reason of his will is implied, which is as cogent and binding as all reasons in the world, till he makes it appeare that ceaseth; this is very cleare; but the second Proposition is that whereon the strength or weaknesse of the Argument in this dispute lies; let us see therefore whether it speaks home for their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges who cannot speak for themselves, yea or no.</p>
            <p>That which I am to prove, is this, That the reason of Gods command for signing Infants, &amp;c. continues in the same force under the Gospel that it was in under the Law; and then if any one now decline the practise, Ile be bold to say unto him what doest thou? and take my proof thus.</p>
            <p>The reason of the Command for signing Infants of Believers under the Law, with the first signe or seale of the Covenant,
<note place="margin">Minor prov'd. Gen. 17.7. &amp;c.</note> was this promise, <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy seed,</hi> as is evident <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8. compared with the 9, 10, and 11. <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,</hi> where this promise of God, and the application of the first seale are knit into a dependance one upon another, <hi>I will esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish my Covenant between me and thee, &amp;c. to be a God unto thee, and to thy seed after thee, therefore thou shalt circumcise every
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117189:13"/>male, as a token of the Covenant,</hi> verse 11. But this same rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the command continues in force under the Gospel; God doth as truly say to every believing Gentile now, <hi>I am thy God, and the God of thy seed,</hi> as he did to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of believing Gentiles, so he is called, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. Therefore I may conclude, that believers under the Gospel have the same command for signing their Infants with the first seale of the Covenant of Promise [which now is Baptisme] as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had to signe his under the Law, with the first signe &amp;c. which then was <hi>Circumcision;</hi> and now sirs, if the blessing of
<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 3.14, 29.</note>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> be come upon you, and if you be heires accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Promise, you may easily see where to finde a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for baptizing your <hi>Infant-seed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will be necessary to examine what is alledged by those of your way for weakning the first Proposition before I proceed to prove the Minor. Now the only thing of any weight that I know is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> was not a pure Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel Covenant, as appeares, say they, by his promising <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> temporall things, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.8. therefore we may not argue from thence to the Covenant of Grace under the Gospel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I answer.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> The Scripture nowhere cals that Covenant a mixt Covenant, but on the contrary notwithstanding any civill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of temporall things it is held forth as pure a Covenant of Grace as may be;
<note place="margin">The major clear'd.</note> the Apostle tels us plainely that this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was confirmed of God in Christ, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. which I think is enough to make it a pure Gospel Covenant. Christ was never the Testator of any Covenant but that of Grace. Outward things, as appurtenances altered not the Covenant, nor made it mixt at all, unlesse that Covenant we live under be mixt too, for outward things are promised to believers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gospel, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, this Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> is called a Covenant of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2, 3. <hi>of Grace, verse</hi> 4. <hi>of Faith, verse</hi> 13. and I am perswaded that <hi>Abraham</hi> had not beene called <hi>the Father of the Faithfull,</hi> if believers had stood in a different Covenant towards God, with that in which he stood; as for dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in the manner of administring and dispensing that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, they matter nothing if there be no difference in those
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117189:13"/>Evangelicall promises which make it a Covenant of Grace, but no man is able to make this appear; therefore this exception weakens not our Proposition, nor the Argument at all.</p>
            <p>Now to go on to the proof of our second Proposition in the Argument, which is,
<note place="margin">Minor prov'd.</note> that the reason of the command for signing Infants, &amp;c. even this promise, <hi>I will be thy God and the God of thy seed,</hi> continues in full force under the Gospel, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre you to that Scripture. <hi>Acts</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.39. to make it good. <hi>The promise is unto you and to your Children.</hi> What promise? Why, this must needs relate to a former engagement, yea, and that too made unto them to whom the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> speaks, <hi>viz.</hi> Jewes; and I know not to what engagement this can have refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, if not unto Gods promise made to <hi>Abraham</hi> of <hi>being his God and the God of his seed after him.</hi> Certainly he is one of those that are blind and yet have eyes,
<note place="margin">Es. 43.8.</note> who sees not from this Text that this very promise is in force and appliable to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers under the Gospel; and if this stand good, then the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for signing our Infants with the first signe of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, <hi>viz.</hi> Baptisme, stands good too; for this promise is the reason which God gives of his precept; God will owne a Believers children therefore he will have them markt for his.</p>
            <p>Those exceptions that are laid against the witnesse which this place brings to prove the birth-priviledge of Believers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren under the Gospel, I shall briefly take off.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This promise, say some, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Excep. </seg>1</label> is of extraordinary gifts of the Spirit, as the gift of tongues, faith of miracles, &amp;c. with which Christians in that Primitive age were ordinarily endued.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How doth this suit with the promise made to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>I will be thy God, and &amp;c.</hi> unto which I have shewed you the text relates. If it be meant of extraordinary gifts, <hi>Abrahams</hi> believing seed before Christ had them not, yet to them the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise was made good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is impossible, refer the Text to what promise you will, that this should be the meaning of it; for then all believing Jewes should have had extraordinary gifts which they had not; yea, and all Believers to the end of the world might run to God for extraordinary gifts by prayer from this very promise; for it is of use to the end of the world, as appeares by the latter
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117189:14"/>part of the verse, <hi>Even to all that the Lord shall call:</hi> yee very few Believers, I presume, pray for such gifts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Excep. </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But these words <hi>[At many as the Lord our God shall call]</hi> expound the Apostles meaning, which is this, their children should receive the promise if the Lord called them; this I know is mainly urged by diverse of your judgment, and gloried in; but friends, without any cause.</p>
            <p>I <hi>answer.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> That this particle <hi>[Even]</hi> with that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>Whom the Lord our God shall call,</hi> has relation to the next foregoing sentence, <hi>viz. those that are afar off,</hi> for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of that, and not unto this sentence <hi>to you and your children;</hi> so that the Apostle speaks thus much, <hi>The promise is made to you and your children for the present, and when the Lord shall call those that are afar of, and strangers to the Covenant of promise,</hi> they and their children shall be heires to the promise as well as you and your children are now.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Apostle had meant to apply the promise onely to those who should be called of God to believe then it had beene needlesse to have made any mention at all of children; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly he would onely have said, the promise is unto you Jewes, and to all that are afar off when God shall call them: but the holy Spirit sets downe nothing in vaine; therefore surely the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-seed of Believers have some portion in the promise, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are mentioned as well as their Fathers; <hi>to you, and &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That cannot be the Apostles meaning which utterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes the scope he aimes at, and that is to shew the Jewes they shall be bettered rather then worsted by believing in Christ; and he would very hardly have made them believe this, should he have left their children (who were alwayes till now reckoned in Covenant with them) in as poore a condition as the most barbarous Heathens in the world; they are but afar off; and when God shall call them, the promise is to them. I tell you the taking away a childs priviledge goes near the heart of a parent; and think but what a bad argument this would have beene to bring in the Jews. 'Tis cold comfort to hear that their children should be made as much aliens to the Common-wealth of Israel by their Fathers embracing the Gospel, as the very Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans. Surely this would stave off the Jewes from Christ, rather
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117189:14"/>then bring them on, and thus I leave you to judge of the weight of this Exception.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Objection.</hi> But 'tis said, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Excep. </seg>3</label>
               <hi>the Promise is to you and your children,</hi> you that are Jewes and the seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> not to the Gentiles and their children; now if this be not made good, the Argument fals, because we are Gentiles by nature; and thus I haue heard <hi>S. O.</hi> say, <hi>That if he knew a child of</hi> Abraham <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the flesh, he would baptize it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I <hi>answer.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> If believing Gentiles live under the same Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that <hi>Abraham</hi> and his seed did [which has been proved] then though they were none of his seed, 'tis safer to apply the whole promise to them. I <hi>am thy God and the God of thy seed,</hi> then to cut off and circumcise the tenor of the Covenant, and to say unto Believers now. God is onely your God, not the God of your children; is not this to make a maine and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial alteration in the Covenant? and to rob Believers of one of the most precious comforts they have by promise, even Gods owning their seed? which they cannot be assured of as the Jewes were, without their children be admitted to the first signe or seale of the Covenant, which is Baptisme now under the Gospel, as I shall prove by its succeeding Circumcision, by and by.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are not Gentiles the seed of <hi>Abraham?</hi> Then I would be resolved in this, whether Christ took upon him onely the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Jewes, or of Jewes and Gentiles both? If onely of the Jewes, how must the Gentiles be saved? If of both then how will you construe this Text, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16. <hi>He took upon him the seed of Abraham,</hi> if you will not allow the Gentiles by any meanes to be <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed? but yet further.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis plaine in the Gospel that Faith makes a Believer the child of <hi>Abraham;</hi> yea, and a surer heire to the promise, <hi>I will be thy God and the God of thy seed,</hi> then carnal descent from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> loynes doth. <hi>Abraham</hi> had two seeds, one descend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from <hi>Ishmael,</hi> and another from <hi>Isaac;</hi> all that came from <hi>Abraham</hi> were not children, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7. <hi>But in</hi> Isaac <hi>shall thy seed be called. Isaac</hi> was his speciall seed, and typ'd out his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving seed under the Gospel, for <hi>verse</hi> 8. they which are the children of the flesh, these are not, [that is, not in so peculiar a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117189:15"/>manner] the children of God as the believing seed, for the children of the promise are the seed, the seed by way of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie, that is, the prime seed. And marke I pray you, how the same Apostle explaines and applies this to our purpose, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.28, 29. The Galatians were Gentiles, but being believers, <hi>Wee,</hi> saith the Apostle, <hi>as</hi> Isaac <hi>was are the children of promise,</hi> and so the special seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> the Galatians were no more of <hi>Abrahams</hi> naturall seed then we are, but by Faith they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came his prime seed and heires apparent to all the Promises as <hi>Isaac</hi> was, who is said in the next verse to be borne after the Spirit as well as Gospel-believers are. And sirs, shall we make the Covenant curtail and narrow to <hi>Abrahams</hi> prime seed, and halve the Promises to them, when as they are full and large to his worser seed? the Apostle will not suffer this, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>If yee be Christs, then are yee</hi> Abrahams <hi>seed, and heires according to the Promise,</hi> which surely needs must be <hi>according</hi> to the full extent of that Promise made unto our Father <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> for if it be not ours so fully as it was his, then we are not heires <hi>according</hi> to the Promise; If our seed be exempted, it fals much short of what was said to him, <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy seed.</hi> And marke, Friends, I beseech you, that was Gospel which was preached to <hi>Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>In thee shall all Nations be blessed;</hi> not only his naturall seed, that was but one Nation; but all that were of the faith, shall be blessed as children, of what Nation soever, <hi>verse</hi> 7. For Faith was imputed to <hi>Abraham</hi> in uncircumcision, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.10, 11. to this end, <hi>that he might be the Father of all them that believe,</hi> though they be not Circumcised. And truly I wonder, since the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel is so cleare, that Believers are <hi>Abrahams</hi> children, that any man dare rob them of any comfort or priviledge wherewithall he was invested by that Promise to which they are more sure heires then any of his natural seed, as I think is made plaine to the easiest of your capacities. But lastly,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Do believing Gentiles come into Covenant as the Jewes were cast out? if they do, then they bring in their children with them; for the Jewes Infants were cast out with them, and then God is the God of Believers and their seed still; though they be not the naturall branches of the Olive,
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.17.</note> that is the carnall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117189:15"/>seed of <hi>Abraham, of whom as concerning the flesh Christ came, Rom.</hi> 9.5. if they do not, then the Apostles allusion from graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing cannot hold good; for when a scien is graffed into any stock,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.17.</note> all the twigs and branches that grow out from it partake of the fatnesse of the root. Thus in our case, the root may be the Covenant of God; the naturall branches now broken off with their twigs, are the natural seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> even the Jewes; the branches wild by nature graffed into that root or stock, Gods Covenant, are believing Gentiles who come in with their seed or twigs that grow from them, else surely they cannot be said to be graffed in as the Jewes were cut off.</p>
            <p>But peradventure you may say as some do, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> that Christ is that root or stock the Apostle speaks of, and not Gods Covenant, therfore we cannot say Infants as twigs are taken into Covenant if they be not in Christ, which we cannot tell who are and who are not.</p>
            <p>This cannot be from the Apostles scope in that Chapter which is mainly to prove that the rejection of the Jewes is not irrecoverable; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> and one argument that he uses in the proof of this laid downe <hi>ver.</hi> 16. is, <hi>if the root be holy, so are the branches;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.16.</note> now this root must needs be the Covenant or God or their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ancestors who derived inlike sort holines to them, as the first fruits being holy derive holinesse (by Gods institution) to the whole lump, and as the root being holy, deriveth holinesse (by Gods Covenant) to the branches; or else he misseth the scope in his Argument, which is to shew that the Jewes shall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grassed into Christ, and become holy, because their root is holy; which will strongly follow, if we take <hi>Abraham,</hi> or the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his seed for the root, but not if Christ be taken for the root; this is good arguing, if <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> or the Covenant of God with him and his seed be holy, then the Jewes (although now broken off) are or shall be holy also, for Christ imparts his holinesse to none but such as are actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in him by Faith; but the Covenant of God or our holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors may derive a federall holinesse to their seed, though not actually in Christ; else the Apostles Argument touches not, much more shall these which be natural branches be graffed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own Olive-tree, <hi>verse</hi> 24. and if it did not, how are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117189:16"/>the unbelieving Jewes <hi>beloved for their Fathers sakes?</hi> ver. 28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> So many as are believers, come into Covenant, and none others, for the Apostle saith, <hi>By Faith yee stand,</hi> ver. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I answer.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> If Believers exclusively, that is, those and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come into Covenant. <hi>viz.</hi> no Infants or Non-believers, [for we must distinguish Non believers from unbeievers, such as are not come up to a capassity of professing Faith (though they may have Faith <hi>Seminally,</hi> that is, in the Root) these may be called Non-believers, and such are all Infants, yet I dare not say they are all unbelievers] if I say, onely actuall Believers come into Covenant;
<note place="margin">v. 20.</note> then onely such as were actually in unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief were cast out; for the Apostle saith as well, Because of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief they were broken off, as, <hi>By Faith ye stand;</hi> now, 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their Infants were broken off with them; and that they were all actuall unbelievers, and such as rejected Christ at their Fathers casting off, I presume you dare not affirme; and if not, then that such onely as are actual Believers were taken into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.24.</note> I dare by no meanes affirme. For if Christ be the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of a better Covenant in respect of its better administration, what man may take the boldnes to say Believers infants are left out in the Gospel administration which is better, and yet taken in under the Legall administration, which was the worse? Or if any one will be so bold as to say it, who may safely credit him? surely leaving out a Believers seed is something materiall to speak the Covenant-dispensation under the Gospel more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable then that under the Law; which, how harshly it sounds in the eares of such as look at Christ Jesus as the enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his peoples priviledges by his coming in the flesh, I leave you to judge.</p>
            <p>And thus I have made good my Argument, the reason of that command given to <hi>Abraham</hi> for signing his infants with the first signe or seale of the Covenant of Grace is of force with Believers under the Gospel; God is still both <hi>their God and the God of their seed,</hi> therefore the command is still in force; and now the first signe or seale of the Covenant by the institution of Christ, is <hi>Baptisme.</hi> A Believers Infant hath the like right to that Ordinance, which <hi>Abrahams Infant-seed</hi> had to <hi>Circumcision</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the continuance of that Ordinance.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:117189:16"/>
            <p> But it may be objected, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> you take this for granted in your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that <hi>Baptisme</hi> comes in the roome of <hi>Circumcision,</hi> and that it is a seale of the Covenant of Grace, which very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deny, and you have not proved.</p>
            <p>If the former of these be proved, the latter cannot be denied; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> if <hi>Baptism</hi> succeed <hi>Circumcision,</hi> it must needs serve for the same use, or else there is no succession; If a Master turne away a man-servant to day, and hire a maid-servant to morrow, she she cannot be said to succeed him, if she be not hired to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that work which the manservant did; or though there be not the same reason of Baptisme and circumcision in all respects, yet if Baptisme be an Ordinance set up by the appointment of Christ to serve for the fame spirituall ends that circumcision did,
<note place="margin">Exercitac. pag. 3. &amp;c.</note> [which Master <hi>Tombs</hi> the ablest man reputed that ever writt for your way, readily grants] then I do not know how you will avoid the succession of Baptisme to circumcision. You may see it proved more fully by Master <hi>Cotton,</hi> Master <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall,</hi> Docter <hi>Homes</hi> and others upon this point, to whom I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre you if you may be permitted to read them; I will onely open that one place <hi>Coloss.</hi> 2.10, 11. for the proofe of it,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.10, 11, 12.</note> and then passe to your main Objections.</p>
            <p>The Apostles scope in that chapter is to perswade the Colos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians of our absolute and full compleatnesse in Christ under this Gospel administration of the Covenant of Grace that we might not hanker after mens traditions or the rudiments of the world, least it might be Objected,
<note place="margin">v. 8, 9.</note> we are not so compleat in Christ as the Iewes were under the old dispensation of the Covenant; they had circumcision, but we want it, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the spirituall benefits signified and sealed by it, which is the cutting off of the body of the sins of the flesh; the Apostle answereth, we have that by the circumcision of Christ, in whom also ye are circumcised, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">v, 10.</note> but least it should again be object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed we want an outward signe and seale of this, <hi>Paul</hi> answers, <hi>neither do we so, for we are buried with him in baptisme,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">v. 12.</note> which signifies the putting off of the body of the sins of the flesh; what doth baptisme then but succeed circumcision, being an outward signe of the same thing substituted in the place of that abolished Rite? nay give me leave a little further, I think this place is very full for the baptizing of infants; for baptisme
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117189:17"/>must succeed in the same subject, or else it cannot be said to succeed at all. If one of our late Kings sons should be crowned King of <hi>Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ireland</hi> only, he could not be said to succeed the King of <hi>England,</hi> because the subject of his Government in respect of latitude is chang'd, and he comes not in his fathers room as King of <hi>England;</hi> this therfore I say, pleads the right of infants very strongly; if baptisme doth succeed circumcision, it must be in the same subject, and that extended to the full lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude that circumcision was, <hi>viz</hi> beleevers infants as well as themselves; and indeed the Apostles Argument is not satisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unlesse our infants are to be baptized, for it might be obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted we are not yet as complete as the Iews were, because that besides their own circumcision they had their infants circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
<note place="margin">Deut. 30.6.</note> to signe and seale unto them that God would circumcise not only their owne hearts, but the hearts of their infant-seed also as is promised; but we in our baptisme, though we have a signe and seale that God will wash and purify our hearts, yet we have nothing to confirme this unto us that he will wash the hearts of our infants also. But admit the baptisme of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants as well as of our selves to succeed in the place of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to the Iews and their infants, and then the Apostles Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment proceedeth fully, and concludeth invincibly, that we are as compleat in our baptisme, as the Iewes were in their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision.</p>
            <p>By our baptisme we enter into Covenant with God, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> which infants are not capable of, because to a Covenant it is necessary that there be a mutuall consent and agreement of both parties, covenanting together.</p>
            <p>To this I answer, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> that as the Heavens are higher then the earth,
<note place="margin">Cotton.</note> so are the wayes of God higher then our wayes, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the ways of his grace &amp; of the Covenant therof; with men indeed mutuall agreement is necessary to a Covenant,
<note place="margin">Esa. 55.9.</note> but not with God; the Lords appointment makes a Covenant, whether the creature consent to an Agreement or no. We read of Gods making a Covenant,
<note place="margin">Gen. 9 9, 10, 11.</note> not only with <hi>Noah</hi> and his seed, but also with every living creature, that he would never send a flood to destroy them from off the face of the earth any more; here was only an appointment of God to this Covenant; could the beasts stipulate or agree? surely an infant is as capable of covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117189:17"/>us the Fowles of the Ayre or the beasts of the Field.</p>
            <p>But your main objection, is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Infants are not believers; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label> but the Gospel of Christ ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves none in the Lords Covenant, nor admits any unto it's pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges or Seales, (of which the Ordinance of Baptisme is one) but believers; and therefore we read of none Baptized but upon profession of faith, confession of sins &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I answer, 1. Neither did the Old Testament approve any. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> in the Lords Covenant but such as believed; yet infants of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters were approved to be in Covenant then; and I presume you will not stick to grant they were as much unbelievers then, as infants are now; but it is one thing to approve the person of any one in Covenant, and cleerly another thing to approve him to be in the Covenant: as for example, God did never approve either <hi>Iudas</hi> in his Apostleship, nor <hi>Demas</hi> in his Ministry, yet he did approve it that both of them should be admitted to their Ministry.
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.23.</note> God did never approve of <hi>Ishmael</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> family, yet he approved it that he should be in his Fathers house, and also be admitted to the Covenant of his Father and the Seal thereof, till his own prophannesse cast him out, and I have clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it that the promise runs to Gentile believers and their seed as fully now, as unto the Iewes and their seed of old, and if un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe in infants then denyed them not a place in the Covenant, I cannot see why it should do it now.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I dare not say that infants are unbelievers; for though they be not capable of the hearing of Faith, the preaching of the Gospel which ordinarily begets belief, yet they are capable of the Spirits teaching; [this I am perswaded you will readily grant me, unlesse you think, as your teacher <hi>S. O.</hi> doth, that a childs soule is not perfect, as being
<note n="*" place="margin">Not created by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of spirits: so he held <hi>Febr.</hi> the 8.</note> begotten by the Father and Mother] which Spirit being the principall part of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall seed of the word, can beget the grace of the new birth, and Faith without meanes; and if infants for want of hearing the word in their own persons want faith, and for want of Faith may not be Baptized, then for want of Faith they cannot be saved; for so run the words, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.15, 16. If for unbelief they must not be baptized, for unbelief they must then be damned.</p>
            <p>If you say, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Excep. </seg>
               </label> that's meant of the Lords way of saving grown
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117189:18"/>men, infants are saved another way, and upon other terms; this makes a breach for me to go out at for the baptizing of infants, as well as for your selves to go out at for their salvation; for I can say, and that more truly, infants are baptized another way, and upon other termes then grown men, and hearers of the word are, <hi>viz.</hi> upon their parents Faith which intitles them to that Ordinance; if either of an infants parents do believe, he takes hold of the Covenant for his Child, because in believing the glad Gospel tydings published, he beleives this, that as God has proclaimed himselfe the God of believers and their seed, so he will be his God, and the God of his seed; and now his children are no longer Pagans and Infidels,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.16.</note> but the children of the faithfull and holy, in whom God hath Covenanted to work Faith, and the grace of Regeneration in the elect seed, and to offer both it and the means thereof unto all the seed, till they utterly reject it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I answer, the Apostles in their practise of administring baptisme onely upon profession of Faith, set us not up a rule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst infant baptisme, unlesse it be recorded that they did refuse absolutely to baptize infants, if offered to them, because they could not professe Faith in Christ. Is it safe arguing from the not doing of a thing to a non-equity of doing it? Especially if there be a rule for it when occasion is offered, as in our case by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving parents tendering an infant up to God in Covenant up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this promise, <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy Seed.</hi> Or is it good reasoning thus, because we read not that the Apostles baptized any infants, therefore surely they baptized none? E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially when it may be as probably gathered from what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that they did, as that they did not. 'Tis recorded that they baptized whole houshoulds,
<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 16.15, 33. 1 Cor. 1, 16.</note> and 'tis no where said there were no infants in them. We do require profession of Faith before baptisme from Proselytes and men of grown yeares, whether Iewes or Pagans, as the Apostles alwayes did; but shew us any ground from the word excluding the infants of such as professe Faith and are baptized, either from the Covenant or from the Seal of it, and then you shall see us quickly lay down our plea for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant baptisme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quest. </seg>
               </label> But is there any danger to defer an infants baptisme till we see God outwardly call it?</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:117189:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> Yes, there is danger, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> even of the Parents transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing a rule, they fulfill not all righteousnesse, lay hold upon the Covenant but to the halfes, leaving their seed out of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, and doing what in them lies to disinherit them; for when God cals the children of beleevers to a Profession of faith, the promise comes not to them at all as the seed of beleevers, but as beleevers themselves: unlesse therefore infants be baptized and so accounted of Gods family, till they cast themselves out of it, a believers child hath no more Priviledge from his Parents faith, then a Pagan-infant hath from its fathers unbeliefe. But this we affirm, That the children of beleevers do come on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to beleeve by reason of the Covenant of grace, which God hath made with beleevers and their seed; for by that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant he hath promised to write the law of faith, as of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saving graces in their hearts, that they may come in Gods time and way to enjoy all other saving Priviledges of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as did their fathers before them; and hereupon infants have a right to that first signe of the Covenant, Baptism, which alone they are capable of having administred to them while infants. And friends, if calling for children outwardly to come unto Christ will suffice you in this, they cannot be said to come before they are called in <hi>Mark</hi> 10.14. and if Christ call for them by his promise to their fathers, they do truly come [and upon an outward call too] though brought in their parents armes; their root is holy, so are the branches by a Covenant-ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linesse at least, which the Apostle speaks plainly to, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. and though that place be eluded by your Teachers, with saying infants are holy that are sanctified to the beleeving Father as the unbelieving wife is, and no otherwise, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Excep. </seg>
               </label> he having an holy use to them both: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Answ. </seg>
               </label> yet let me tell you that this is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weak evasion; for when <hi>Paul</hi> saith <hi>the unbeleeving yoake fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low is sanctified,</hi> he doth not leave it so without a restriction, but faith, <hi>he or she is sanctified to the beleever,</hi> which must needs limit the sense to the believers use; but speaking of children, he leaves out that limitation, and saith not, they are holy to the beleever, but positively, <hi>they are holy;</hi> now to be sanctified to a believer, and to be holy, are very different, and therefore let not us make them the same; sicknesse is sanctified to a beleever, so are bonds and imprisonment; is sicknesse therefore and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117189:19"/>holy? the fallings of Gods children into sinne are sanctified unto them, God enables them to make a sanctified use of their fals; but I dare not say that fallings into sinne are holy; the childes holinesse therefore is more then the sanctification of the yoake-fellow unto her husband; and if that be not Gods reckoning it to be within his holy Covenant, for its fathers sake, I would gladly learne of you what it is.</p>
            <p>And thus by the guidance of those beams of light which have broken in to my spirit from above by the word, I have broken through the clouds of your maine objections, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented that sacred truth of God, (for which I have contended) cleare to the view of every gracious heart that stands in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall awe of Gods word. If you seek for a command to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize your infants, I have told you where to find it; if you would know how that command can stand with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles practice, I have let you see; and I doubt not but such as lay sure hold upon the blessing of <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith, will own every Priviledge of <hi>Abraham</hi> as a believer for theirs, amongst which this is a choyce one, even the encovenanting their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-seed with them. I have but briefly put into your hands and somewhat rodely, that which other of Gods faithfull witnesses choycely anointed from above have spoken in this point: for I thinke it almost impossible that more should be said, then what they have written for evidence of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and had not their writings been hid from you, I doubt not but you would have been baptized into a spirit of better obedience then for the present many of you are. The Lord give you hearts willing to retreat, when you see your selves beaten back from your errours by the strength of truth, and not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately to persist and go on,
<note place="margin">2. Thes. 2.11.</note> deceiving and being deceived, as men given over to a spirit of strong delusion, and utterly fallen from your own stedfastnesse.</p>
            <p>I had thought to have spoken something about the point of generall atonement with which you are strangely taken,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16, 17.</note> and very impatient of all men contrary-minded; but let me intreat you seriously to weigh how your tractate is handled already by Mr. <hi>Stalham</hi> of <hi>Suffolke</hi> in that businesse,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bams</hi> vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, tio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> if it be lawfull for you to look upon any thing that makes against Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> or tends towards the shaking your hearts in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117189:19"/>he tels you is a truth. I desire you only, as touching this matter, in the feare of God to consider</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether Election be not a truth as clearly held out in the word, as that of Christs dying for all? if you say not, Ile bind my selfe to every one of you upon the forfeiture of my faith, through Gods assistance to make it cleare, when ever you shall call me; and for the present look into these Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16. to the 24. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4, 5. 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.13. weigh them well, and deal not deceitfully with your souls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Since Election can be taken but one way, even for Gods chusing and calling a people out of the world for himselfe;
<note place="margin">Joh. 15.19.</note> and Christs dying for all may be taken severall wayes, as either for to save all, or to procure some benefit for all; whether it be not more safe to take Christs dying for all in that sense in which it may consist with Election, then in that sense where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it utterly overthrows it; a gracious heart is as jealous of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry truth of God, as of any one single truth; and though Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> say we bind mens hands, and tie up their legs with a kind of an eternall decree, yet I shall take leave to tell him, if that decree which he mocks at take no hold of him, better were it for him, though Christ died for all, never to have heard syllable of the name Jesus.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether Christs putting all men in point of means only, into a possibility of salvation, can stand either with this Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God or the certain salvation of any. For friends, that which on is only possible to be, its possible it may not be.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether there be any just ground for you to charge the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with making the way of salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too narrow when they make it broad enough for all belevers? let prophane unbeleeving wretches complain of this, it doth not to well become you who professe the holy faith; <hi>you know streight is the gate and narrow is the way, &amp;c.</hi> and he that makes it broad enough to take in unbelievers, speaks wickedly for Gods grace, and let him answer it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether the Gospel may not be preacht freely and fully, though sinners be never told that Christ died for all? <hi>I</hi> say tis his dying for sinners makes it Gospel, and not his dying for all sinners; for evidence of this look into 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:117189:20"/>
            <p> And now let me from what ha's been spoken advise you, that you would take heed of being too hasty in judging those [to whom you cannot vouchsafe the name of Ministers] as teachers of lies, and men leading people in false wayes, meerely from accusations drawn up against them by heedlesse gainsayers; if 'tis crime enough to be accused, I wonder where you will find an innocent man. Speak not the Ministry Antichristian, till your selves or <hi>Samuel Oates</hi> can prove they counterworke Christs designe of saving soules: I am perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded some of you are the Seale of their Ministry; if so, you requite them very ill,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.2.</note> when instead of gratifying God in them, you do even despise them in your hearts, if not hate them with a perfect hatred; but they are willing to take up with that of their Master, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.20. and will never faile to account it their greatest honour to be <hi>made a Spectacle unto the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.9. &amp;c.</note>
               <hi>and to Angels and to men,</hi> yea to be trampled under foot as the mire in the street for the cause of Christ and his Gospel: the Lord in whose hands they are, will enable them to approve themselves as his Ministers, in much patience, in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.4. &amp;c.</note> in necessities and distresses, by honour and dishonour, by evil report and good report, as deceivers and yet true, as poore yet making many rich, as having nothing and yet posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing all things.</p>
            <p>Thus I take my leave of you, desiring that you would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looke every expression [if there have any such escaped from me] which savours not of the Spirit of meeknesse. If any of you be unsatisfied in any thing here laid down by me, I am ready to take it up, and to maintaine what I have written, as knowing God will own it for his truth, and not suffer it to fall by reason of the weaknesse of his hand who is yours and every mans in Gospel service.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JO: DREW.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:117189:20"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 8. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>JO. DOWNAME.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>